A Guide to the Virginia Geological Survey, Records, 1834-1903
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records, 1834-1903
Library of Virginia
24815
3.45 cubic feet [7 boxes]
Virginia Geological Survey.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Emma Savage Rogers, May 10, 1903.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Geological Survey of Virginia was conducted in two phases. First, under an act passed by the General Assembly on March 6, 1835, a geological reconnaissance of the state was made to compile data of a general nature on geological features, and chemical compositions of soils, minerals and mineral waters for a report to the next session of the General Assembly.
Then the geological survey itself, which was devoted to a more detailed study than the reconnaissance, was established by an act of the General Assembly on February 26, 1836. This survey was to provide a careful and accurate chemical examination and analysis of various soils, and principal ores, marls, saline and mineral waters. Other goals of the survey were to determine the height of principal mountains, construct a complete geological map of the state for engraving, and to collect and catalog specimens of rocks, fossils, ores, mineral, compounds, and organic remains, so that there would be a sufficient amount to distribute to institutions of higher learning. Both acts called for the appointment of a geologist by the Board of Public Works, and in each case Professor William Barton Rogers of the University of Virginia was appointed. He was responsible for supervising the survey, submitting annual reports on its progress, rendering geological sections and a geological map of the state, analyzing minerals and waters for their chemical content, and distilling all the collected data into a final report at the conclusion of the survey. Members of his staff included William A.E. Aikin, George W. Boyd, Caleb Briggs, Jr., Charles B. Hayden, James Rogers and Israel Slade.
William Barton Rogers was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, on December 7, 1804, the son of a professor of physical sciences. He attended the College of William and Mary in 1820 and 1821, taught school at Windsor, Maryland, in 1826, was appointed a lecturer at the Maryland Institute in Baltimore in 1827, and succeeded his father in 1828 as professor of chemistry and physics at the College of William and Mary. On February 9, 1835, when enthusiasm for a geological survey of Virginia was running strong in the General Assembly where a bill had been introduced, Rogers appeared before a House committee appointed to study the matter and drafted the committee's report to the House of Delegates recommending the establishment of the survey. The next evening, February 10, 1835, Rogers delivered an extemporaneous address to a joint session of the House and Senate describing the benefits of a geological survey to the state. As a result of Rogers's efforts, the General Assembly passed a bill on March 6, 1835, authorizing the Board of Public Works "to appoint a suitable person to make a geological reconnoissance of the state, with a view to the general geological features of our territory... and to report to the next general assembly a plan for the prosecution of a geological survey of the state." The board appointed William B. Rogers to the position on March 25, and he accepted it on April 2. His brother Henry Darwin Rogers was appointed as his assistant.
The geological survey was continued by annual appropriations of state funds until 1842, when the General Assembly terminated the project because of a financial recession. In 1844 Rogers engaged Russell Smith, a Pennsylvania artist, to draw sketches and sections for the final report. Unfortunately, the money necessary to complete the report was never authorized by the General Assembly, although Rogers continued to hold the records of the survey until his death in the hope of receiving funds.
Rogers spent the summer of 1835 in the field, making notes for his report, collecting samples of rocks, ores, and mineral waters for chemical analysis, and compiling data for geological sections of the state to show the different mineral strata. In August he accepted a call to the chair of natural philosophy at the University of Virginia. The first half of the school year was employed in teaching and in drawing sections, analyzing specimens, and drafting his report to the General Assembly. The report was submitted to the House of Delegates by Governor Littleton W. Tazewell as president of the Board of Public Works on January 11, 1836. The report met with the approval of the General Assembly, which passed an act on February 29, 1836. Rogers was expected to make annual reports on the progress of the survey, as well as a final report when the survey was completed.
In the spring Rogers gave his assistants their orders for the season, pointing out particular areas for investigation. Until the school year ended Rogers was confined to the University, maintaining contact with his assistants in the field through the unreliable mail system. The assistants tried their best to keep Rogers informed as to their activities and whereabouts, their problems with sick horses, broken instruments, and lack of funds. As soon as he could, Rogers took to the field himself, visiting his assistants, conducting his own investigations and traveling to other states to study and compare the geology of Maryland, Pennsylvania, and New England. When the University reconvened Rogers returned to Charlottesville, once again relying on the mails to communicate with his asistants. As winter approached the assistants visited Rogers on their way to their homes, turning reports and specimens over to him for study during the winter. By the first of the new year Rogers had prepared his annual report for the General Assembly and was making plans for the ensuing season. After the Panic of 1837, Rogers was forced to worry each year about whether the survey would be continued for another year.
In 1853 Rogers resigned his position at the University of Virginia, wishing to move to Boston, Massachusetts, to work with his brother Henry. Before leaving Virginia, however, Rogers spent almost three months in early 1853 in Richmond, in a last, futile attempt to persuade the General Assembly to fund the final report. On March 8, 1854, Rogers left Virginia for Boston and a new career as a founder and first president of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Even after he left Virginia, Rogers continued to seek funding for the final report, but did not succeed. On May 30, 1882, as he was delivering a commencement address at MIT, Rogers collapsed and died.
Rogers's widow, Emma Savage Rogers, began a time consuming project of sifting through her husband's papers, selecting some for publication and destroying others. She presented the surviving papers to the Virginia State Library in two lots, the first aobut 1900 and the second on May 10, 1903. At first the papers were supposed to be the personal papers of William B. Rogers and were so described. However, the Archives staff came to realize that the documents were in fact state records which Rogers kept in his possession pending the writing of his final report. Accordingly, the records are now regarded as a subgroup within the records of the Board of Public Works. Records primarily concerned with the adminstration of the funds for the survey by the second auditor and the Board of Public Works have been described already by John S. Salmon, comp., in Board of Public Works Inventory (Richmond: Virginia State Library, 1978), entry 21, "Geological Survey."
William E. A. Aikin, of Maryland, appointed assistant geologist effective June 1, 1837. Resigned April 13, 1839. Was teaching at the Baltimore Medical School in 1873; George W. Boyd, of New York, appointed assistant geologist on May 1, 1838. He died of asthma on September 23, 1840, in the home of William B. Rogers at the University of Virginia, Charlottesville; Caleb Briggs, Jr., of New York, appointed assistant geologist on June 1, 1839. He was paid for his services to July 1, 1842; Charles B. Hayden (January 22, 1817-January 28, 1883), of Connecticut, attended the College of William and Mary, and probably was a student of William B. Rogers, 1834-1835. Appointed assistant geologist effective April 1, 1837. Board of Public Works received notice that he had "retired from the service" on June 11, 1840. He taught school in Smithfield, Virginia, and later became a lawyer; Samuel Lewis, appointed assistant geologist effective June 1, 1840. He was paid for his services to March 1, 1841; Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., appointed assistant geologist on April 15, 1840. He was paid for his services to June 2, 1842; Henry Darwin Rogers (August 1, 1808-May 29, 1866), of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, appointed assistant geologist on April 2, 1836. Resignation received by the Board of Public Works on May 8, 1837. Directed New Jersey and Pennsylvania state geological surveys, later collaborated with William B. Rogers on a paper concerning mountain elevation; James Blythe Rogers (February 11, 1802-June 15, 1852), of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, appointed assistant geologist in May 1837. Resignation received by the Board of Public Works on April 15, 1840. Reappointed assistant geologist on May 1, 1841. He was paid for his services to August 1, 1842. The major contribution of his career was the development of methods of chemical analysis.
Robert Empie Rogers (March 29, 1813-September 6, 1884), of Baltimore, Maryland. He was a chemist with the Pennsylvania Geological Survey and was professor of chemistry at the University of Virginia, where he collaborated with William B. Rogers, and at the University of Pennsylvania; Israel Slade, of Pittstown, New York. Employed by William B. Rogers (accepted offer on April 16, 1838) who paid him with his own funds. Appointed assistant geologist on April 15, 1840. He was paid for his services to July 1, 1842; A Maxwell Walker, appointed topographical surveyor on May 5, 1836. His resignation was received by the Board of Public Works on March 11, 1837; William Thompson Russell Smith (April 26, 1812-November 8, 1896), known as Russell Smith, was born in Glasgow, Scotland, but moved to Pennsylvania in 1819 with his parents. The family eventually settled in Pittsburgh, where Smith became interested in painting and drama. He combined the two interests by painting scenery for the stage, and had a successful career that took him eventually to Philadelphia, Baltimore, and Washington, D.C. It was probably while he lived in Milestown near Philadelphia during the late 1830's and early 1840's that Smith became acquainted with William B. Rogers on one of the geologist's visits to the area. Rogers engaged Smith to execute a series of drawings of significant geological formations in Virginia for use in Rogers's projected final report on the state geological survey. Smith travelled to Charlottesville in June 1844, and from July to September he and Rogers explored western Virginia. Smith used the resulting sketches for his own benefit as well as for Rogers's, making them the basis for oil landscapes for exhibition. Eventually he mailed the sketches to Rogers for him to keep.
Scope and Content Information
The records are divided into three series: Series I: Correspondence of William B. Rogers, 1836-1903; Series II: Reports, sections, lists, and field notes, 1834-1884; and Series III: Drawings of Russell Smith, c. 1844.
Series I: The correspondence to Rogers was primarily from his assistants. Also included are letters from George W. Summers, member of the House of Delegates, and James Brown, Jr., Second Auditor of Virginia. There were also letters from Rogers and a letter from Emma Rogers, his wife, to William W. Scott, Librarian of the State Library.
Series II: The field notes and reports are from 1834 to 1884. William B. Rogers was one of four brothers, all of whom were noted chemists and geologists. Two brothers, Henry Darwin Rogers and James Blythe Rogers, served as his assistants at different times during the conduct of the survey, while the third, Robert Empie Rogers, contributed his observations on the geology of the Northern Neck. Rogers's other assistants, appointed by the Board of Public Works, were: William E. A. Aikin, George W. Boyd, Caleb Briggs, Jr., Charles B. Hayden, Samuel Lewis, Thomas S. Ridgeway, Jr., Henry Darwin Rogers, James Blythe Rogers, Robert Empie Rogers, Israel Slade and A. Maxwell Walker. In the spring, Rogers gave his assistants their orders for the season, pointing out particular areas for investigation, and as winter aproached the assistants gave him reports on the geological, chemical and topographical discoveries which they had made.
Series III: Rogers personally hired a Pennsylvania artist, Russell Smith, to make drawings for the final report; Smith and Rogers spent most of the summer of 1844 afield for this purpose. The 51 sketches depict geographical features and are done on paper and cardboard, in ink, pencil, pastels, oils and watercolor.
Organization
Organized into the following three (3) series: I. Correspondence of William B. Rogers from 1836 to 1903; II. Field notes and reports from 1834 to 1884; and III. Drawings of Russell Smith, c. 1844.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence of William B. Rogers, 1836-1903
  The correspondence to Rogers was primarily from his assistants. Also included are letters from George W. Summers, member of the House of Delegates, and James Brown, Jr., Second Auditor of Virginia. There were also letters from Rogers and a letter from Emma Rogers his wife, to William W. Scott, Librarian of the State Library.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - George W. Summers, Richmond, to [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, February 15, 1836, George W. Summers, Richmond, to [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, notifying him that the bill providing for a geological survey has passed the House of Delegates and is expected to pass the Senate easily; also discussing the printing of Rogers's geological report by order of the General Assembly. 2 pp. with address leaf. Summers was a member of the House of Delegates from Kanawha County in 1836.
    - J[ames]Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 5, 1836, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, enclosing a copy of the act providing for a geological survey of Virginia; informing him that the Board of Public Works had, on April2, 1836, appointed him geologist; and asking for a written proposal of how he intended to caryy out the intentions of the Act. 1 p. with address leaf. James Brown, Jr. (June 1780-January 3, 1859) was Second Auditor of Virgniia from March 1, 1823, to December 31, 1852, and Secretary of the Board of Public Works from March 1, 1823, to March 31, 1851.
    - James E. Heath, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 6, 1836, James E. Heath, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning a check written for Rogers on the Bank of Virginia and the safe arrival of some geological profiles for the engraver; also mentioning "the pleasure afforded me" in meeting "Mr. Bancroft," to whom he showed some of "our ancient state records." 2 pp. with address leaf. James E. Heath (July 8, 1792-June 28, 1862) was First Auditor of Virgniia from January 8, 1820, to February 28, 1850. George Bancroft (October 8, 1800-January 17, 1891), American historian and diplomat, author of a ten-volume History of the United States.
    - R[obert] E[mpie] R[ogers], Westmoreland Courthouse, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 24, 1836, R[obert] E[mpie] R[ogers], Westmoreland Courthouse, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his observations of the geology of the Fredericksburg--King George--Westmoreland area, particularly in regard to the Stratford cliffs on the Potomac River, where he found fossil vertebra and ribs. 4 pp. Robert Empie Rogers (March 29, 1813-September 6, 1884), chemist and geologist, was a brother of William Barton Rogers.
    - C[harles] B. Hayden, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 28, 1836, C[harles] B. Hayden, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the bad weather, his lack of clean clothes, observations of a geological nature, and his plans for travel. 3 pp. with address leaf. Charles B. Hayden was appointed assistant geologist by the Board of Public Works on May 4, 1837, to be effective retroactively to April 1, 1837. A Charles B. Hayden was a student at the College of William and Mary during the 1834-1835 session while William Barton Rogers taught there.
    - A. M[axwell] Walker, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, June 11, 1836, A. M[axwell] Walker, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, giving his address as "Mr. Duvals Powhatan House," and discussing his progress in drawing maps. 2 pp. with address leaf. Walker was appointed topographical surveyer by the Board of Public Works on May 5, 1836. His resignation was received by the Board on March 11, 1837.
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hezekiah Daggs, Botetourt Springs, to Professor [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, March 23, 1837, Hezekiah Daggs, Botetourt Springs, to Professor [William B.] Rogers, University of Virginia, sending him five bottles of sulphur water, a sample of limestone, and a piece of shale; describing the strata encountered in sinking his shafts; asking whether Rogers thinks he will strike coal; and inviting Rogers to stay at his house if he visits Botetourt Springs in the summer. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - C[harles] B. Hayden, Smithfield, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 6, 1837, C[harles] B. Hayden, Smithfield, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, describing his plans to survey the branches of Pagan Creek for blue marl; complaining of the difficulty of making adequate notes on such small maps as he has to use; and commenting on the general business of the survey. 2 pp. with address leaf.
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 9, 1837, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, correcting an error in his previous letter to Rogers concerning the salaries of Rogers and his assistants, and acknowledging with regrets the receipt of Henry Rogers's resignation as assistant geologist. 1 p. with address leaf. Henry Darwin Rogers (August 1, 1808-May 29, 1866), geologist, was best known for his 1858 report on the geological survey of Pennsylvania. Brother of William Barton Rogers. He was appointed assistant geologist for the Virginia geological survey on April 2, 1836.
    - C[harles] B. Hayden, Hot Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, May 9, 1837, C[harles] B. Hayden, Hot Springs, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, concerning the lack of mail from his family and reporting on his progress in examining Dibbrell's, Sweet, and other springs in the region near Covington. 3 pp. with address leaf.
  - Correspondence to William B. Rogers, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, March 20, 1838, J[ames] Brown, Jr., Second Auditor's Office, Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, informing him of the Board of Public Works's approval of his plans for the ensuing season and reviewing matters concerning Rogers's expense account. 1 p. with address leaf.
    - Timothy Taylor, Jr., Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, March 22, 1838, Timothy Taylor, Jr., Richmond, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, asking for an analysis of a sample of limestone which Taylor had given Rogers for James McIlhaney. 1 p. with address leaf. Timothy Taylor was a member of the House of Delegates from Loudoun County in 1838. James McIlhaney had been a State Senator representing Loudoun and Fairfax counties and again held that office during the 1839-1840 session.
    - V.[two initials illegible] Alexander, Baltimore, Maryland, to Dr. W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Charlottesville, April 7, 1838, V.[two initials illegible] Alexander, Baltimore, Maryland, to Dr. W[illiam] E. A. Aikin, Charlottesville, recommending Septimus Norris of Havre de Grace, Maryland, formerly employed by Benjamin Henry Latrobe, for any position which might be available with the Virginia Geological Survey. 1 p. with address leaf. William E. A. Aikin was appointed an assistant geologist by the Board of Public Works effective June 1, 1837. Benjamin Henry Latrobe, Jr. (December 19, 1806-October 19, 1878), son of the architect and engineer, was assistant engineer for the construction of the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad in 1838.
    - Judge J. M. Allen, Syracuse, New York, to William Taylor, Washington, D. C., April 9, 1838, Judge J. M. Allen, Syracuse, New York, to William Taylor, Washington, D. C., asking Taylor to obtain a copy of William Barton Rogers's report on the geological survey of Virginia, or that part of it dealing with "Brine Springs, and the manufacture of Salt"; offering to reciprocate the favor by sending Rogers any geological reports he might want; and reviewing a report on salt he had just obtained. 1 p. with address leaf. William Taylor (October 12, 1791-September 16, 1865)was a physician as well as a member of the U. S. House of Representatives, March 4, 1833-March 3, 1839, from Onondaga County.
    - George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 14, 1838, George W. Boyd, New York, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, accepting his offer of a position as assistant geologist with the geological survey of Virginia; desiring a change in the terms of employment with regard to travel expenses and servants; stressing that his geological experience has not included minerals of the tertiary region; describing his immediate travel plans; and enclosing letters of recommendation from James Renwick and John Torrey. 3 pp. with address leaf.
    - James Renwick, Columbia College, New York, to W. B. Rogers, Charlottesville, April 14, 1838, James Renwick, Columbia College, New York, to W. B. Rogers, Charlottesville, recommending George W. Boyd for the position of assistant geologist. 1 p.
    - John Torrey, College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, to W. B. Rogers, Charlottesville, April 14, 1838, John Torrey, College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, to W. B. Rogers, Charlottesville, recommending George W. Boyd for the position of assistant geologist. 1 p. with address leaf. George W. Boyd was appointed assistant geologist by the Board of Public Works on May 1, 1838. He died on September 23, 1840, at the home of William Barton Rogers in Charlottesville. James Renwick (May 30, 1792-January 12, 1863), a leading topographical engineer and chemist. John Torrey (August 1796-March 10, 1873), physician, chemist, and botanist whose naturalist system of classification had great influence on American botanists.
    - Israel Slade, Pittstowne, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, April 16, 1838, Israel Slade, Pittstowne, New York, to William B. Rogers, University of Virginia, accepting his offer of employment and expressing his gratitude. 2 pp. with address leaf. Israel Slade served as an assistant geologist and was paid in part by Rogers with his own personal funds.